<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from the New Exchange, or The commonvvealth of ladies, drawn to the life, in their severall characters and concernments.</title>
            <author>Neville, Henry, 1620-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E590_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203016</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863120</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863120</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115302</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115302)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 90:E590[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from the New Exchange, or The commonvvealth of ladies, drawn to the life, in their severall characters and concernments.</title>
                  <author>Neville, Henry, 1620-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, of women without grace, 1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Nevile.</note>
                  <note>Variants: (1) mispaginated [2], 2 [i.e. 21], [1] p. (p. 21 misnumbered 2); (2) paginated [2], 21, [1]p. (i.e. p. 22 not numbered).</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Jan: 30th 1649", the 50 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  England --  London --  Social conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  Social life and customs --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115302:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Newes from the New
EXCHANGE,
OR THE
COMMONVVEALTH OF
LADIES,
Drawn to the Life, in their
ſeverall Characters and
Concernments.</p>
            <bibl>Martialis. <hi>lib. 4. Epig.</hi> 71.</bibl>
            <q>
               <l>Quaero diu, totam greſsus agitando per urbem,</l>
               <l>Si qua puella negat, nulla puella negat.</l>
               <l>Tamquàm fas non ſit, tamquam ſit turpe negare;</l>
               <l>Tanquàm non liceat, nulla puella negat.</l>
               <l>Caſta igitur nulla eſt? caſtae ſunt mille. Quid ergo</l>
               <l>Caſta facit? non dat; non tamen illa negat.</l>
            </q>
            <bibl>Ovidius.</bibl>
            <q>
               <l>—Casta eſt quam nemo rogavit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the year, of Women without
Grace, 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="characters">
            <pb facs="tcp:115302:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115302:2"/>
            <head>Newes from the New-EXCHANGE,
or the
Commonwealth of Ladies,
drawn to the Life, in their
ſeverall Characters and
Concernments.</head>
            <p>THere was a time in <hi>England,</hi> when
men <hi>wore the Breeches,</hi> and debar'd
women of their <hi>Liberty;</hi> which
brought many grievances and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
upon the <hi>weaker veſſels;</hi> for,
they were conſtrained to converſe only with their
<hi>homes and cloſets,</hi> and now and then with the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman-uſher,</hi>
or the <hi>Foot-man</hi> (when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y could
catch him) for variety: So that in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe dayes,
there was no ſuch thing as the SERVANT,
the FRIEND, or the INTIMATE in
ordinary; nor durſt they be acquainted with the
<hi>mode</hi> of <hi>Drinke, Dice,</hi> and <hi>Tobacco;</hi> nor <hi>role</hi> and
convert their ſmoks into <hi>Colanders,</hi> to ſtrain healths
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115302:3"/>
of <hi>Sack</hi> into <hi>Beer-glaſſes,</hi> and take them off aſtride
upon mens ſhoulders. In conſideration whereof,
and divers other inconveniences, by the tyranny
of men, the <hi>Ladies Rampant</hi> of the times, in their
laſt <hi>Parliament,</hi> knowing themſelves to be a part
of the <hi>free people</hi> of this Nation, unanimouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
to aſſert their own <hi>freedoms;</hi> and caſting
off the intolerable yoke of their <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,</hi>
have voted themſelves the <hi>Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi>
both at home and abroad, and ſetled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
in the poſture of a <hi>Free-State,</hi> as may appeare
by their <hi>Practices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place, for the well ordering of their
<hi>Militia,</hi> they have liſted themſelves under the
conduct of the Right Honorable the Counteſſe of
<hi>Kent,</hi> and the old Counteſſe of <hi>Exceter;</hi> who
ought to lead the <hi>Van,</hi> being experienced Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
that have paſſed through all Offices in <hi>Venus</hi>
Warrs, from a <hi>Corporall</hi> to a <hi>Colonell.</hi> Theſe two
are the only pillars of Nobility and Hoſpitality;
who, to breed up the <hi>young Fry</hi> in the Miſteries of
the <hi>Sexe,</hi> have erected an <hi>Academy,</hi> which is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
every <hi>Sunday</hi> night at the Counteſſe of <hi>Kent's</hi>
and every <hi>Thurſday</hi> at my Lady of <hi>Exceter</hi>'s. There
<hi>Suppers</hi> are reckoned moſt convenient, becauſe the
<hi>Bed</hi> follows, and it is judged the beſt way of
diſgeſtion after the <hi>Lectures,</hi> they never being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
any other Subject, but WHO with WHO,
<hi>Miſtreſſes</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> and the <hi>Act of well-doing,</hi>
which muſt needs breake the <hi>Academy</hi> of <hi>well ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115302:3"/>
and ſoon make the <hi>Italian</hi> Knight loſe all
his Cuſtome, for going the wrong way to worke
with our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ladies.</p>
            <p>And if he dare diſpute the matter, wee will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
it to my Lady <hi>Carliſle.</hi> This is a Lady indeed,
that ſeven years ſince took ſaile with <hi>Preſbytery,</hi>
being charged in the <hi>Fore-deck</hi> by Maſter <hi>Hollis,</hi> in
the <hi>Poop</hi> by Maſter <hi>Pym,</hi> whilſt ſhe clapt my Lord
of <hi>Holland</hi> under hatches. And this was a lucky
<hi>Supply</hi> at that time, becauſe <hi>Toby Matthewes</hi> and
<hi>Wat. Mountague</hi> were both <hi>fled for Religion.</hi>
About 3 years ſince, being weary with that <hi>facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
ſhe revived a correſpondence upon the <hi>Royall
accompt;</hi> among the reſt with divers <hi>foreine Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors;</hi>
eſpecially <hi>Monſ. Believerey,</hi> till ſhe
was put in the <hi>Tower,</hi> where ſhe now pines away
for want of <hi>freſh-Cod,</hi> and knoweth not which way
to lead her <hi>Nags</hi> to water, ſince the <hi>State</hi> hath cut
off all her <hi>pipes</hi> of intelligence.</p>
            <p>After her comes the old Lady <hi>Peterburgh,</hi> who
would faine be yong. A <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Lady too,
that caſts a fad looke with her eies for the downfall
of her <hi>Faction,</hi> and ſings the <hi>lamentation of a ſinner</hi>
for the loſſe of Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> but above all for the Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable
loſſe ſhe had in <hi>Tom. Gell,</hi> when my Lady
<hi>Rutland</hi> got him from her.</p>
            <p>'Twere pitty my old Lady <hi>Devonſhire</hi> and theſe
two ſhould be parted, for, the <hi>Preſbyterie</hi> was ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
firſt in her houſe by the <hi>Scots Commiſſioners;</hi>
where my L. <hi>Louden, Lauderdale,</hi> and <hi>Dumferling,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115302:4"/>
were clapt in her <hi>hole of Repentante,</hi> to forward the
work of <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we talk of <hi>Reformation,</hi> God help my
Lady <hi>Salisbury,</hi> whoſe Sinnes are as big as her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
and whoſe faults are better known at home
than, abroad, ſince the death of the old Duke of
<hi>Buckingham</hi> and my Lord of <hi>Holland.</hi> A very
charitable Mother ſhe is to all her Children; but
eſpecially to her daughter my Lady <hi>Sands,</hi> having
helpt her to a <hi>Touch,</hi> with her Son in Law my Lord
<hi>Liſle,</hi> though my Lord of <hi>Salisbury</hi> himſelf, like a
croſſe Father,<note n="*" place="margin">My La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die <hi>Sands</hi> was war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming her Brother <hi>Liſles</hi> drawers by the fire Side.</note> came in and took her airing his
<hi>Drawers.</hi> This Lady <hi>Sands</hi> continues her <hi>Clack</hi>
going ever ſince, to draw <hi>griſts</hi> to the <hi>Mill,</hi> and
is at this time one of the greateſt <hi>Courſers</hi> upon the
<hi>New Exchange;</hi> She out-drinks a <hi>Dutch man,</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies
a <hi>Courteſan,</hi> and is good at all <hi>Games,</hi> but loves
none like <hi>In and In,</hi> and ſometimes ſhe is for <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</hi>
In league with her are all the <hi>Hat-and-fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Gallants,</hi>
the <hi>feather</hi> being the proper <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphick</hi>
of her Condition, and the Badge of
her <hi>faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for her good Siſter, the yong Lady <hi>Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi>
She hath been a very ſad woman ever ſince
the death of my <hi>Lord Iohn;</hi> but ſince that, She
hath been rid of her <hi>Qualm</hi> by <hi>Tom Killegrew,</hi> who
is now gon Ambaſſador from <hi>Ierſey</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> on
purpoſe to fetch her a <hi>Muſk-cod</hi> to perfect the
Cure.</p>
            <p>This Family is both large and godly, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115302:4"/>
we muſt not forget my Lady <hi>Cranborn;</hi> who
lives in a <hi>Scotiſh miſt</hi> betwixt light and darkneſſe
ſo that groping often for Truth, She now and then
layes hold upon the <hi>Preacher,</hi> and puts him beſide
the <hi>Text,</hi> in an error. She playes above-board with
Mr. <hi>Sackvile,</hi> under-board with Mr. <hi>Sterry,</hi> and
ſeverall other <hi>Captains</hi> that uſually preach <hi>before
her</hi> and the <hi>Councell of State.</hi> She hath preferred
one <hi>Lee</hi> Lecturer at <hi>St. Martin's,</hi> to read <hi>lectures</hi> on
Sunday nights to the whole <hi>Family,</hi> concerning
<hi>due Benevolence;</hi> which gave occaſion to Miſtris
<hi>Peele</hi> (an <hi>Intimate</hi> of theirs) to commend his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
above all others.</p>
            <p>And now, nor forgetting an over-thwart neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor
of theirs we muſt think of my Lady <hi>Forſter;</hi> an
old <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> and a yong <hi>Saint;</hi> one whoſe propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
puts us in mind of her <hi>Excellencies,</hi> and he
that meanes to board her, muſt put off his doublet
and ſwim, it being of the ſame ſize with a <hi>Fiſh-Pond:</hi>
yet it is ten to one if he ſcape ſinking, ſince
ſhe is ſomewhat of kin to <hi>Goodwin Sands,</hi> having
ſwallowed up many <hi>Families,</hi> many <hi>Blew Garters,
Georges, Earls,</hi> and <hi>Baronies</hi> innumerable. Among
them, as the lateſt (though of a long continuance)
is the Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> of <hi>Parham;</hi> who hath now
taken a journey to the <hi>Barbado's</hi> and means to pipe
her one way ſince he cannot another; In Order
whereunto he hath provided her a whole plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Tobacco, it being her proper Element; ſo that
ſince my Lord finds <hi>Smoak,</hi> Sir <hi>Humphry</hi> may in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115302:5"/>
time have <hi>Bacon.</hi> I would have this Lady well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd
in the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> ſhe being now a great
<hi>Retailer of Courteſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly her Daughter my Lady <hi>Prat</hi> (for
ought I ſee) is reſolved to keep up the <hi>Trade,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
an Husband for the purpoſe. This is that
doughty Knight Sir <hi>George Prat,</hi> once celebrated
in <hi>Comedy,</hi> and pawned upon the <hi>Stage</hi> (as well as
at the <hi>Tavern)</hi> in a <hi>Ioynt-Stool</hi> for a Reckoning.
Hee, Sir <hi>Samuel Luke, Ieffery,</hi> and little <hi>Trott,</hi> may
help to make up the Nine <hi>Worthies</hi> amoug the <hi>Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi>
and might paſſe for rare Champions in <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi>
to erect a new <hi>Common wealtb</hi> among the
<hi>Monkies.</hi> Indeed, take Sir <hi>George,</hi> hornes and all,
and he is a very formidable <hi>Monster;</hi> ſo that 'tis
no wonder if his <hi>Lady</hi> be reprehended by her <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
for being <hi>Bull'd by an Urchin:</hi> She is a great
<hi>wit,</hi> and playes with an old <hi>Sophiſter</hi> (Dr. <hi>Smell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmock,
alias</hi> Mr. <hi>Osbaston)</hi> who jerks her both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind,
and before; therefore Mr. <hi>Lenthall,</hi> though
he have playd <hi>Truant</hi> a great while, may the rather
ſcape a whipping.</p>
            <p>Come, take your Turn Mrs. <hi>Gamlyn;</hi> for, you
have had many a one by that excellent Squire of the
Body yong <hi>Lenthall,</hi> who hath the art to love if the
Women love him. They ſay, <hi>Northamptoc</hi> makes
love one hour to you, and he beats the brains of it
out in a quarter. This Gentleman broaches <hi>maxims</hi>
very dangerous to the Common-wealth of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<hi>viz. That there is no woman honeſt. That wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115302:5"/>
would become unneceſſary in the world, if that
damnable principle of honeſty ſhould be profeſſed. That
originally there was no ſuch quality as honeſty, only it
was inſinuated by the perſwaſions of the firſt mother, to
keep women from being debauched in their nurſes arms.</hi>
All which hath been applauded, and ſeal'd to, by the
ſame <hi>Gentleman,</hi> over and over.</p>
            <p>Now, as a brave<note n="*" place="margin">Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Het<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maphro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite.</note> 
               <hi>Woman-man-of-mettle,</hi> heigh
for my Lady <hi>Hungerford.</hi> Since Sir <hi>Edward</hi> is in
Heaven, the fitteſt <hi>mate</hi> for her upon Earth,
muſt needs be <hi>Annis-water Robbin,</hi> For they may
fit one another by turns, and be beholding to no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.
This <hi>Lady</hi> over-rid and excarnated, no leſſe
than three of her women in her husbands life-time;
and hath left no part of foure <hi>Gentlemen-uſhers</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
in the world, but their <hi>periwigs;</hi> but the fifth
ſcapes yet, and may perhaps for a twelve-month.</p>
            <p>Room next for my Lady <hi>Kingsmell;</hi> who having
been lately in <hi>France,</hi> hath brought over ſome <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian</hi>
tricks with her. The only wit in that houſe
is <hi>new lechery,</hi> and her Daughter is <hi>voſtre Serviteur.</hi>
The Mother ſhould have been married to my Lord
of <hi>Norwich,</hi> at his coming out of priſon, but that
of late he is become as dry as his jeſts, and the talke
of the town diverted the humor.</p>
            <p>But my Lady <hi>Rutland</hi> (God wot) is a more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
Lover; for, now that her Lord is out of
Town, nothing can ſtave her off from <hi>Tom. Gell.</hi>
This fellow the world ſuſpected to be Eunuch to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115302:6"/>
my Lord of <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> but now ſhe commends him
for the ſweteſt man in the world though of late
ſhe hath a great ſtroke too with <hi>Harry Martyn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we talk of a <hi>ſtroak,</hi> I can tell you of a
notable <hi>Striker</hi> one Mrs. <hi>Luſon,</hi> who hath blowne
up and broke ſo many <hi>French, Dutch,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi>
Merchants, that none of late durſt deal with her but
<hi>Hugh Peters;</hi> who (I hear) hath pawned halfe the
<hi>fleet</hi> at <hi>Milford</hi>-haven to provide her a <hi>new yeares
gift;</hi> and this in imitation of his Maſters at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi>
who ever put the Charges of their <hi>Leche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
upon the accompts of the <hi>Publique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This policy of <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> puts us in mind of
godly <hi>Gravener,</hi> he that is <hi>Commiſſary</hi> to my Lady
<hi>Fairfax;</hi> who hath pawned his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
couple of <hi>Flanders</hi> horſes, to make ſure of
Miſtris <hi>Luſon:</hi> And ſhe I think hath paid him pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
well; for the poor <hi>Gent.</hi> hath ſpit himſelfe into
a <hi>Night cap,</hi> and the next Remove may be into a
<hi>Coffin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ever the <hi>new Common weal</hi> be routed, it muſt
be by this <hi>Lady;</hi> for, put a little <hi>Gunpowder</hi> to her
<hi>Mercury,</hi> and you may ſoon blow up my Lord
<hi>Bradſhaw.</hi> He (they ſay) hath audited her Phiſicke
<hi>Bill,</hi> and the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>State</hi> finds many faults in it
As <hi>Inprimis,</hi> one purge for a <hi>clap</hi> ſhe had from Sir
<hi>Harry Mildmay,</hi> which was much invenom'd by
one he caught the morning before from <hi>Beſſe</hi> the
<hi>Begger wench.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> a Plaiſter for the <hi>ſwelling</hi> in her <hi>Groin,</hi> that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115302:6"/>
Mr. <hi>Marten</hi> gave her from a <hi>Shanker</hi> of his, which
he caught from the <hi>Wench</hi> he ſtole from his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Member
Sir <hi>Roger North.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> an <hi>Aſtringent</hi> for a <hi>Gonorrhaea,</hi> given her by
Mr. <hi>Scot,</hi> which hath been entailed upon him and
his Family, ever ſince he ſtrain'd at the <hi>Brewers</hi>
daughter behind the <hi>Ale-fat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> for a <hi>Pimple,</hi> which my Lord of <hi>Denbigh</hi>
entailed on the Top of her <hi>Belly</hi> from the Tip of his
<hi>Noſe.</hi> The <hi>Pothecary</hi> pleaded this cure was extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary,
becauſe the <hi>Rubyes</hi> in my <hi>Lords</hi> noſe,
might have cauſed a <hi>Carbuncle</hi> in her <hi>Cabinet,</hi> had it
not been prevented (according to my <hi>Lord's</hi> owne
direction) with an <hi>emollient Clyster</hi> over night, a
Doſe of <hi>Pills</hi> in the morning, and an <hi>electuary</hi> from
the ſame <hi>Lord</hi> the night following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> for fluxing, fuming, ſoking, and Tubbing
of <hi>Heveningham,</hi> a worthy <hi>Member;</hi> yet all will do
no good; For, this <hi>Lady</hi> and he have been ſo long
of the <hi>ſame humor,</hi> that he cannot be cured of a
<hi>Rhume,</hi> that hangs on both ſides his mouth, ſo that
ere long he may be <hi>Chapfall'n.</hi> This <hi>Malady</hi> hath
been much exaſperated by an ill <hi>prepared flux,</hi> which
hath left him more of <hi>Mercury</hi> than <hi>Venus</hi> in his
Body. Ask my Lady <hi>Lake</hi> elſe, who did what wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
could for him, plyed him with <hi>Cordials</hi> and
warm <hi>Plaiſters:</hi> but <hi>broke his head</hi> when ſhe ſaid,
<hi>She wondred hir Cozen</hi> Heveningham <hi>would have to
do with ſo rotten a woman.</hi> As ſhe wounds ſome, ſo
ſhe <hi>ſhaves</hi> others; for ſhe has made Mr. <hi>Love</hi> a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115302:7"/>
wofull Example, who never wore any beard ſince
her firſt acquaintance.</p>
            <p>Oh, let us not now forget Miſtris <hi>Duns,</hi> a Lady
every jot as <hi>Independent</hi> as the former, ſhe hath
payed Tribute to all the Deputies of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and
will not now forbear her Coſen <hi>Cromwell.</hi> Shee
keeps mighty Intelligence too with his wife, and
ſhe with <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> with Miſtris <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
ſhe with <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> he with Madam <hi>Caſtlehaven,</hi>
as <hi>Cromwell</hi> with Mrs. <hi>Lambert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now enter my Lady</hi> Craven, <hi>at a conference
over her Cups.</hi> Fie ſiſter fie; never a Beer-glaſſe of Sack to
Sir <hi>William Sidley's</hi> health? yes, my Lady <hi>Craven,</hi> here's
one, fill a Brimmer, to that part of my Siſter <hi>Craven</hi> which
Sir <hi>William</hi> loves beſt. Tis well fill'd, and fairely drunke.
Now to do you right, my Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> here is to you; to the
finiſhing of Sir <hi>Williams</hi> deſires, let it be how, where, and
when he pleaſes. Come, my Lady <hi>Mary Howard,</hi> take
courage; though thy fortune be but ſmall, yet having
a good ſtroke, thou ſhalt drinke <hi>Dormer</hi> into Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
            <p>Tis the wonder of the world, Why Sir <hi>Kenelm
Digby,</hi> ſhould be ſo mad for my Lady <hi>Middleſex,</hi>
ſince he boarded her and the Gallies at <hi>Scanderoon</hi>
much about the ſame time, and hath rid at Anchor
ever ſince. Tis a very hard matter to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſhe be, a <hi>Lady</hi> or <hi>Leviathan.</hi> Sure, none but
<hi>Goliahs</hi> weapon can fit her <hi>Scabbard,</hi> nor can any
hand but his with the <hi>ſix fingers</hi> ſufficiently <hi>ſeele</hi> her;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115302:7"/>
and he that will pleaſe her (which ſhe abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
loves) muſt convert a <hi>Weavers beam</hi> into a <hi>dildo.</hi>
If ſhe and Sir <hi>Kenelme</hi> go on with the <hi>Match,</hi> then
let the <hi>Saints</hi> beware; for, I beleeeve <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog</hi>
will come of the <hi>Progeny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what thinke you of my Lady Marchioneſſe
of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> and Colonell <hi>Warren?</hi> Though my
<hi>Lord</hi> be her Husband, yet the Colonell is the man.
Though my <hi>Lord</hi> have a good <hi>Bable</hi> by deſcent, and
may play well, yet the Col. hits the <hi>blot</hi> oftner in
his <hi>Ladie's Tables.</hi> She is often ſick, and as often
ſwels, and, by the opinion of all <hi>Doctors,</hi> no cure
is like that in private with her Colonell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boles</hi> was an able fellow too once, before he came
to be my Lady of <hi>Bath's</hi> Gentleman uſher: But
you may gueſſe how the VVorld goes with him
now; for he <hi>dwindles</hi> every day, and (ſome ſay)
the <hi>Calves</hi> of his legs are left in his Ladies Belly;
ſo that when my <hi>Lord</hi> expected a Son, God knows
it proved a <hi>Moon Calfe;</hi> and had it grown up to
have <hi>horns,</hi> my <hi>Lord</hi> might then have hoped it was
of his own begetting.</p>
            <p>Poor <hi>Jack Young!</hi> my Lady <hi>Monmouth</hi> bites hard
too; for, ſhe hath drawn him ſo low, that he
will never make <hi>Mummy;</hi> and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
to prefer him for a living <hi>Skeleton</hi> to <hi>Surgeon's</hi>
hall, as a very neat Subject for an <hi>Anatomy</hi> lecture.
And indeed, it is high time he were ſome way
diſpoſed of, for, his <hi>fore-man</hi> is ſo flag, and his
hams ſo feeble, that my Lady is conſtrained ſtill to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115302:8"/>
cry out [<hi>Thy finger againe,</hi> Jack.]</p>
            <p>I beleeve the <hi>Parſon</hi> too is puzled, to interpret
the barrenneſſe of my Lady <hi>Stanhope,</hi> ſhe gives
him the opening of many a hard <hi>Text,</hi> ſo that he
will have much ado to reſolve the <hi>Tithe,</hi> of her
<hi>Doctrine</hi> into <hi>Uſe</hi> and <hi>Applycation;</hi> for (tis known)
ſhe is much given to <hi>Hunting,</hi> and hath run down
a whole <hi>kennell</hi> at a time for recreation. Her mouth
is (like <hi>mopſaes) O Heavenly wide,</hi> ſo that her <hi>Taile</hi>
being of the ſame ſize in dimenſion, 'tis poſſible
<hi>Stamford</hi> may paſſe throngh her, booted and ſpur'd
to ſeek <hi>new fortunes</hi> in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is another notable <hi>Lady</hi> too, newly come
out of <hi>France,</hi> and knowes all the feats of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
and is now ſet up in <hi>England,</hi> by name my
Lady <hi>Mountague;</hi> all ſpirit of <hi>Sulphur:</hi> for, ſhe
takes fire immediatly, and evaporates without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception;
ſo that we muſt leave her to the skill of
<hi>Ben. Weſton,</hi> to provide a Son for my Lord <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue,</hi>
as the <hi>Prince Elector</hi> did for my Lord <hi>Moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave.</hi>
And if ever <hi>Ben.</hi> mean to effect it, let him
keepher <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> only to himſelfe, and recall her
<hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> which lie <hi>Leiger</hi> for <hi>ſtrong backs,</hi> in
City and Country.</p>
            <p>She trades not ſo openly, but others are as cloſe;
yet <hi>Murther</hi> will out: for, 'tis known well enough
(though carried in private) how often Mr. <hi>Villiers</hi>
hath come the <hi>Back way</hi> over a wall, to the fore way
of my Lady <hi>Savile,</hi> alias <hi>Suſſex;</hi> and ſhe uſually
helps him down in her armes, for feare of a ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115302:8"/>
Newes, newes, The Dutcheſſe hath a Son and
heir, in the abſence of Prince <hi>Rupert.</hi> But—&amp;c.</p>
            <p>If Madam <hi>Newport</hi> ſhould not be link't with
theſe <hi>Ladyes,</hi> the <hi>chain</hi> would never hold; for, ſhe
is Siſter to the famous Mrs. <hi>Porter</hi> (who of late
plaies the <hi>Macquerela</hi> in the behalf of her owne
Son;) and to the more famous Lady <hi>Marlborough</hi>
(whoſe Paint is her <hi>Pander.)</hi> This Lady <hi>Newport</hi>
leads the Lord <hi>Bellaſis</hi> in one hand, and <hi>Iack Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell</hi>
in the other, and cuts a kindnes ſo equally be-between
them, that Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby</hi> needed not
have come in to decide the controverſie. Yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
beat the <hi>Buſh</hi> ſo often, there's no reaſon but
he ſhould catch the <hi>Bird,</hi> and theſe two <hi>Gentlemen,</hi>
when he comes, be turned looſe to ruminate the
Favor.</p>
            <p>And that this <hi>Lady</hi> may not go without her fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
if you are <hi>coloured,</hi> my Lady <hi>Elizabeth Darcy,</hi>
appeare as <hi>Stanhope,</hi> alias <hi>Cheſterfields</hi> Daughter.
Take confidence, ſuch as your Siſter <hi>Stanhope</hi> did,
when ſhe met <hi>Hatton Rich</hi> upon the ſtairs, whilſt
her Husband (good man!) was making his <hi>Will.</hi>
Manage your deſigne well; there is no feare but
you may trail both Sir <hi>Andrew,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Glascock,</hi>
as long as they can crawle, and you ſmile. Theſe
are very tractable <hi>Gent.</hi> and hot-mettal'd; the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
you ſtave them off, the fiercer they come on;
the longer you hold them in play, the more will
the <hi>prize</hi> be valued. This <hi>Madam</hi> is like a <hi>Politique
Merchant,</hi> in our <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and (if ſhe be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115302:9"/>
not taken off by Preferment) may chance to ſpoile
the Trade of all <hi>Stallions</hi> in Penſion, by teaching
the reſt of the Ladies how to prize their Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities.</p>
            <p>My right hand would forget it's cunning ſhould
the example of all women be left out, my Lady
<hi>Cullen,</hi> who in my Lord <hi>Riche's</hi> time was called
my Lady <hi>Mary Cokaine,</hi> but varied her name
when ſhe began to teach Souldi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs how to order
the <hi>Pike.</hi> This <hi>ſilken-Granado</hi> hath blown up ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
a Garriſon; for ſhe ever <hi>fired well,</hi> wounded
one <hi>Captain</hi> ſo that he lies in ſtill, fell furiouſly
on many others; and ſhe hath one <hi>Trick,</hi> that if
you will not charge her, ſhe'll charge you. Upon
theſe tearms ſhe met with a <hi>Colonell,</hi> one <hi>Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi>
whom when ſhe had worn out one way as
well as the other, ſhe <hi>caſhired</hi> him for want of <hi>pay,</hi>
and took over his head <hi>George Porter,</hi> whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne
is to <hi>Levell</hi> her even with his owne principles.
On the other ſide, ſhe, having ſmelt his <hi>Plot,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
to grow weary of him, and plies the <hi>Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi>
but knowes not how to admit another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
his <hi>Mother</hi> and his <hi>Wife</hi> ſtand <hi>Sentinell</hi> at her
elbow.—It is intended, the life of this <hi>Lady</hi> ſhall
ere long come out in <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 'tis an old <hi>Proverb,</hi> there can be no <hi>Play</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
a <hi>Foole</hi> in it. Alas poore Maſter <hi>Pembroke,</hi>
who twelve months ſince was an <hi>Earl,</hi> but now
being made a poore <hi>Commoner</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> hath
rallied his <hi>forces,</hi> and finds it neceſſary to caſhire
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115302:9"/>
my Lady <hi>May,</hi> my Lady <hi>Banbury,</hi> and my Lady
<hi>Crompton,</hi> having been very angry with her, and
deſired her to reſolve him of this Queſtion,<note n="*" place="margin">She dun'd him beyond reaſon for Money.</note> 
               <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
he ſhit Gold?</hi> This poor over-ridden <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
lies now at <hi>Rack and Manger,</hi> with a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bermaid
of my Lady <hi>Herbert's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Zounds,</hi> we are now in a Godly Family; and
they that are the only people in the world, that
know to order <hi>Women:</hi> for, the <hi>Father</hi> keeps two
wives and a Concubine, as priſoners. The Lord
his ſon (a poore <hi>Commoner</hi> too) rid his hands of
one wife, and keeps this very cloſe, though <hi>Jack
Griffith</hi> be in <hi>France;</hi> and ſo doth <hi>James his</hi> too,
though my Lord of <hi>Oxford</hi> be in <hi>Holland.</hi> As for
<hi>Jack,</hi> with his <hi>Spider's ſhanks,</hi> his <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> is not
arived to fourteene yet, or elſe he would take the
ſame courſe as his Brothers, for feare ſhe ſhould
ſuck of the ſame <hi>Teat</hi> with her <hi>Mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVee cannot name my Lady <hi>Crompton</hi> too often.
VVhen <hi>Tom. Temples</hi> ſtock could hold no longer,
neither in <hi>Wit</hi> nor <hi>Money,</hi> ſhe laid him aſide like a
ridiculous <hi>Foole,</hi> and jump't in with my Lord
<hi>Molineux,</hi> who whipt up her Belly here in <hi>England,</hi>
and then ſhe got a <hi>Paſſe</hi> to go to her husband in
<hi>France,</hi> that he might father the <hi>Bantling.</hi> My
<hi>Lord</hi> and ſhe are parted ſince, but how, it is not
known; only we heare of great reſolutions againſt
<hi>Teeming,</hi> profeſſing ſhee will venture no more for
Children: but we fear ſhe muſt have one more to
pleaſe my Lord <hi>Broncker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115302:10"/>
Heigh, now for the nine <hi>Worthies,</hi> who above
all deſerve the <hi>Breeches,</hi> to ride aſtride to the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</hi>
And to lead the <hi>Van,</hi> march couragious yong
Madam <hi>Peterborough,</hi> whoſe Earl is a <hi>Wittoll,</hi> and
her father was a <hi>cuckold,</hi> gramercy old <hi>Peterbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough.</hi>
This Ladie makes nothing of 3. Gallons
of <hi>Usquebagh</hi> to Mr. <hi>Staffords</hi> health, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
the <hi>Gentleman</hi> lends her, his wife payes
him again in the ſame <hi>coyn</hi> at home, according to
my Ladies <hi>maxim,</hi> which ſayes,
<q>
                  <l>Shee's too much Phlegme, a husbands faults can
ſmother;</l>
                  <l>If he take one, tis fit you take another.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Next, enter Madam <hi>Peter,</hi> who was tried by the
Prince <hi>Elector,</hi> and <hi>Harry Compton</hi> was his <hi>Taſter.</hi>
This will neither ſettle Mr. <hi>Vowell's</hi> eyes, nor his
Conſcience; for, he hath liquored her with many
a <hi>Pot,</hi> and toſted her, and ſhe promiſes much in her
<hi>cups.</hi> Beſides her faculty in drink, ſhe is good at
all <hi>games,</hi> but eſpecially at cogging the <hi>Die,</hi> and
the <hi>Cod-peece.</hi> [Though we cannot rank her Aunt
(my Lady <hi>Mary Sheldon</hi>) among the <hi>Nine,</hi> yet it
being pitty they ſhould be parted, ſhe may paſſe for
an <hi>Appendix,</hi> being ſo faſt hung to my Lord <hi>Peter,</hi>
that his <hi>Lady</hi> rambles without ſuſpition, and ſets
down this for a <hi>maxim</hi> of our <hi>Commonweale;</hi>]</p>
            <q>
               <l>That <hi>Ladies</hi> when their <hi>Lords</hi> new loves do mind,</l>
               <l>Should, in revenge, like <hi>Cats</hi> unto their kind.</l>
            </q>
            <p>'Twere pitty the <hi>Third</hi> ſhould be left out who
ought to have been firſt in order. Shew as confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
as you ſpeak, Mrs. <hi>Phil. Mohun,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115302:10"/>
               <hi>Rhetorick</hi> is <hi>Ribaldry,</hi> whoſe Element is <hi>Drinke,</hi>
whoſe wit is in <hi>Baudery,</hi> and whoſe Beauty is bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
with her own Breath, it being a damp that will
kill a <hi>Spider.</hi> She ſwears with a <hi>bon-grace,</hi> makes
<hi>offenſive</hi> and <hi>defenſive</hi> War; offenſive with <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi>
whoſe Lordſhip is an Aſſe, <hi>defenſive</hi> with
<hi>Lenthall,</hi> whoſe courage is wit. This <hi>Lady</hi> will be
ſure to match the man, if ſhe knows the length of
his weapon. She is often purged, but vowes <hi>drink
is the best Phyſick,</hi> and delivers this <hi>maxim;</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>If any thing make women more divine</l>
               <l>Than men, it muſt be quick and mighty wine.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Make room for the <hi>Fourth,</hi> (with the new-elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
Colonel <hi>Corbet)</hi> by name Miſtris <hi>Harris,</hi> ſiſter
to the forementioned <hi>Lady,</hi> who neither in <hi>quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
quality, action, Paſſion,</hi> nor any other <hi>Predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
is any whit leſſe remarkable. She hath lived
theſe 30. years in the ſame extremes that the reſt
of her <hi>Siſters</hi> now begin with. <hi>Tom. Temple,</hi> had
never been arreſted for the 200 l. if he could have
plied her <hi>buſines</hi> in earneſt, as well as laugh at his
own <hi>Jeſts,</hi> Let old gouty <hi>Aſh</hi> of the Parliament
take heed; for, that in the <hi>noſe</hi> is not ſo eaſily
cured as that in the <hi>Toe,</hi> and the Cavalier <hi>Corbet,</hi> &amp;
his Miſtreſſe may chance to make him croſſe <hi>Pothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi>
Bills, and <hi>baudy reckonings,</hi> inſtead of the <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts</hi>
of the Kingdom. For, after a full <hi>beer-glaſſe,</hi>
ſhe ſet down this too for a <hi>Maxim.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>The <hi>Members</hi> ought, now <hi>Cavaliers</hi> are poore,</l>
               <l>If they will ſhare a <hi>Miſtreſſe,</hi> pay the <hi>ſcore.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115302:11"/>
The third of the <hi>Siſters</hi> makes up the <hi>fifth</hi> of our
<hi>VVorthies.</hi> Enter Miſtris <hi>Cambell,</hi> with a <hi>piſſ-pot</hi> on
her head, a <hi>pipe</hi> in her mouth, &amp; a <hi>pintle</hi> in her Tail.
<hi>Aſh</hi> runs through this Family, as his brother-commoner
<hi>Howard</hi> (known heretofore by the name
of Lord <hi>Howard)</hi> runs through the Family of the
<hi>Murray's,</hi> and hath made moſt of their Iſſue free
<hi>Deniſons,</hi> being more <hi>Engliſh</hi> then <hi>Scotiſh.</hi> We
underſtand by Maſter <hi>Cook's</hi> books at the <hi>Bear</hi> at the
<hi>Bridg-foot</hi> (who muſt needs be an exact accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,
having been a <hi>Committee-man)</hi> that from
<hi>Midſummer</hi> to <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> 100 pound ſterl. hath
been beſtowed by Maſter <hi>Aſh</hi> upon this <hi>Lady,</hi> in
<hi>VVine</hi> and <hi>Tobacco,</hi> to cheriſh her in the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
of her moſt rare <hi>Maxims;</hi> of which the
chiefe is,
<q>
                  <l>She that with pure <hi>Tobacco</hi> will not prime</l>
                  <l>Her Noſe, can be no Lady of the time.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now for a <hi>Worthy</hi> in good earneſt, my Lady
<hi>Wildgooſe</hi> (alias <hi>Velledicus,</hi> alias Miſtris <hi>Salkeld)</hi>
who reckons continency either to <hi>husband</hi> or <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi>
the worſt of the ſeven <hi>Deadly Sins;</hi> having
lately reſolved to try all that will try her, though
ſhe paſs the moſt <hi>fiery tryall.</hi> Many a ſad journey
hath ſhe made; but of late two into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to
fit her <hi>Engliſh</hi> meaſure, according to the <hi>Italian</hi>
with S. <hi>Bernard Gaſcoign.</hi> She finds VVine of a rare
quality; for it ſaves the charge of <hi>Vermilion</hi> for
her <hi>Beake,</hi> being at great expence upon her cheeks.
This Lady playes as well at <hi>Beſt</hi> as the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> drinks
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115302:11"/>
well; ſwears enough for ſix of the nine, and hath
been often a Caterwauling with Sir <hi>Iohn Morley.</hi>
Her <hi>Maxim</hi> is.</p>
            <q>
               <l>'Tis not enough that <hi>Ladies</hi> drink, whiff, whore,</l>
               <l>Except they ſwear <hi>God-dammees</hi> by the ſcore.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And now ſince the <hi>widdowes</hi> weare the <hi>buſkins,</hi>
let them tread the ſtage boldly; and ſo enter two
more of our <hi>Worthies</hi> at once, <hi>Aunt</hi> and <hi>Niece,</hi> my
Presbyterian Lady <hi>Stapleton</hi> and my Lady <hi>Campi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
the Cavalier, the one Being drunk at the receit
of the newes of her husband's death out of <hi>France;</hi>
the other very jolly, with Maſter <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi>
in her arms, at the newes of her Husbands
death at <hi>Colcheſter;</hi> and ſince that, ſhe hath a <hi>Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi>
every weeke with no leſſe then five, for varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
The controverſie betwixt theſe two is, who
can drink moſt, and then they quarrell for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.
<hi>Tom Temple</hi> and Col. <hi>Iephſon</hi> are their <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds;</hi>
the firſt of whom loſt his <hi>haire</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
had like to have loſt his <hi>one eie,</hi> in deciding the
buſines. But what care theſe Ladies? Their <hi>maxim</hi> is,
<q>
                  <l>She is no <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> though ſhe rants, drinks, Swears,</l>
                  <l>That doth not ſet her <hi>Servants</hi> by the ears.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To bring up the <hi>Rear</hi> of the <hi>nine,</hi> enter the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable
Lady of an old <hi>Low-country</hi> Colonell, by
name <hi>Cromwell;</hi> who hath run through moſt of
the Regiment, both Officers and Souldiers. Since
her coming to <hi>England,</hi> ſhe hath traded never a jot
the leſſe in the <hi>low-countries;</hi> loves Wine, and of
all Wine, <hi>Sack</hi> in Glaſſes; and of all Glaſſes,
<hi>Beer-Glaſſes.</hi> She keeps a <hi>free Port</hi> for all <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115302:12"/>
and trucks with all Languages and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
Shee is controller of the <hi>Club</hi> among the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;
is excellent at the beginning of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alths, <hi>viz.
To the beſt—in Chriſtendome,</hi> and at the
ending of ſtories, for, ſhe fits them all with a <hi>baudy
Comment.</hi> She is Honored with the title of <hi>Lady-Governeſſe</hi>
to the three illuſtrious <hi>Siſter VVorthies,</hi>
Miſtris <hi>Mohun,</hi> Miſtris <hi>Harris,</hi> and Miſtris <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi>
her chiefe deſigne is to reconcile and compoſe
all differences betwixt the two former, and then
when theſe foure are together, there will be a ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety
for the<note n="*" place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern.</note> DEVILL, their <hi>Maxim</hi> being this;</p>
            <q>
               <l>They're fooles that will not theſe examples follow,</l>
               <l>And once a week meet at the great <hi>APOLLO.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>If any of theſe <hi>Ladies</hi> want a <hi>pouder'd and patch't
old fool</hi> to wait upon Them, let them ſend to my L.
<hi>North,</hi> whoſe Coach and himſelf will be ready at
a Call; eſpecially if it be upon a viſit to my Lady
<hi>Kent's</hi> about ſupper time, where they are all upon
<hi>Free-Quarter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By way of concluſion we are in the laſt place to
give notice of certain <hi>Ladies,</hi> called <hi>Courſers,</hi> whoſe
Recreation lies very much upon the <hi>New Exchange</hi>
about 6. a clock at night; where you may fit your
ſelf with ware of all ſorts and ſizes. But take heed
of my Lady <hi>Sandy's;</hi> for, ſhe ſweeps the <hi>Exchange,</hi>
like a Chain'd Bullet, with Mr. <hi>Howard</hi> in one hand
and <hi>Fitz Iames</hi> in the other.</p>
            <list>
               <item>There is my Lady <hi>Katherine Scot</hi> with Mr. <hi>Salkeld.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The new widdow <hi>Sandys</hi> with Col. <hi>Bredridge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lady <hi>Montague</hi> with Mr. <hi>Brown.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115302:12"/>
The 2. Mrs. <hi>Skipwiths,</hi> with Sir <hi>Iohn Morley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Wintour</hi> in contemplation of <hi>David Walter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mrs.</hi> Kirk <hi>with Col.</hi> Rainsford.</item>
               <item>The Lady <hi>Mary Sheldon</hi> with Mr. <hi>Vowell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mrs.</hi> Luſon <hi>and Sir</hi> Thomas Sandys.</item>
               <item>The Lord <hi>Blaney</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Roper,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lord <hi>Middleſex</hi> and the Lady <hi>Thimblebee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mrs.</hi> Wild <hi>and Mr.</hi> Touchet.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Lady</hi> Crompton <hi>and Mr.</hi> Cranfield.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mrs.</hi> Wenman <hi>and my Lord</hi> Denbigh.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Lady</hi> Cary <hi>and</hi> Dudly Sonds.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mrs.</hi> Crew <hi>and Mr.</hi> Broncker.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mrs.</hi> Finch <hi>for a</hi> VVhiffler.</item>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Jones</hi> and <hi>George Colt,</hi> and ſometimes Mr.
<hi>Coghill.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Kingſmell</hi> all alone.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Corbet</hi> Family with who they can get.</item>
               <item>The Lady <hi>Fulgeum</hi> with the Lord <hi>Northampton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lady <hi>Peter</hi> and the Lord <hi>North.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lady <hi>Downs</hi> and the Lord <hi>Sherwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 7. Siſters of the Lord <hi>Sandys,</hi> and the foure
Miſtris <hi>Somes's,</hi> very fleet <hi>Courſers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lady <hi>Norton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Edwards.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Longevile <hi>hopping before twenty wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
and the Lord</hi> VVindſor, Cum multis aliis, quas
nunc perſcribere longum eſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and many more you may buy; but beware
you repent not your Bargain. In our next <hi>Annals</hi>
(if the humor hold) we will give you a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
Relation. In the mean time,
<q>
                  <l>God bleſs the <hi>Authors</hi> from the Blades that ſwagger;</l>
                  <l>From Poyſon, Piſtoll, from the ſword and dagger.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115302:13"/>
            <head>A Poſt-ſcript to the intelligent Readers.</head>
            <bibl>Martialis lib. 6. Epig. 45.</bibl>
            <q>
               <l>Luſiſtis, ſatis eſt; laſcivi cedite Cunni:</l>
               <l>Permiſſa eſt vobis non niſi caſta Venus.</l>
            </q>
            <bibl>Lib. 5. Epig. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</bibl>
            <q>
               <l>Criſpulus iſte quis eſt, uxori ſemper adhaeret</l>
               <l>Qui <hi>Mariane,</hi> tuae? Criſpulus iſte quis eſt?</l>
               <l>Neſcio quid dominae teneram qui garrit inaurem,</l>
               <l>Et Sellam cubito dexteriore premit?</l>
               <l>Nil mihi reſpondes? uxoris res agit, inquis,</l>
               <l>Iſte meae.—</l>
               <l>Res uxoris agit? res nullas Criſpulus iſte:</l>
               <l>Res non uxoris, res agit iſte tuas.</l>
            </q>
            <bibl>Lib. 7. Epig. 9..ad Olum.</bibl>
            <q>
               <l>Centenis futuit <hi>Matho</hi> millibus: <hi>Ole,</hi> quid ad te?</l>
               <l>Illud diſſimulas ad te quod pertinet, <hi>Ole,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Quod<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> magis curae convenit eſſe tuae.</l>
               <l>Uxor Maecha tibi eſt: hoc, ad te pertinet. <hi>Ole.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sed quid agas, ad me pertinet, <hi>Ole,</hi> nihil.</l>
            </q>
            <bibl>Lib. 9. Epig. 42.</bibl>
            <q>
               <l>Pontice, quòd nunquàm futuis, ſed pellice laevâ</l>
               <l>Uteris, &amp; veneri ſervit amica manus:</l>
               <l>Hoc nihil eſſe putas? ſcelus eſt, mihi crede, ſed ingens,</l>
               <l>Quantum vix animo concipis ipſe tuo.</l>
               <l>Ipſam, crede mihi, naturam dicere rerum;</l>
               <l>I ſtud quod digitis, <hi>Pontice,</hi> perdis, homo eſt.</l>
            </q>
            <bibl>Lib. 11. Epig. 23.</bibl>
            <q>
               <l>Diviſit natura mares; pars una puellis,</l>
               <l>Una viris genita eſt: ut ere parte tuâ.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
